A Finding Aid to the Elizabeth McCausland Papers, 1838-1995, bulk 1920-1960, in the Archives of American Art AAA.mccaeliz
Archives of American Art
Elizabeth McCausland papers
bulk 1920-1960
1838-1995
AAA.mccaeliz
Archives of American Art
45 Linear feet
The papers of art critic, writer, and historian Elizabeth McCausland measure 45 linear feet and date from 1838 to 1995, with the bulk of the material dating from 1920 to 1960. The collection provides a vast accumulation of research data on various artists and aspects of American art, especially the early American modernists and the Federal Arts Projects. Papers include McCausland's extensive research and writing files, particularly on Marsden Hartley, E. L. Henry, Lewis Hine, George Inness, and Alfred H. Maurer. McCausland's correspondence with artists includes a substantial amount with Arthur Dove and Alfred Stieglitz. Her collaborative work with Berenice Abbott on the Changing New York book and series of photographs is well-documented within the collection. Also found are general writings, subject files, files relating to exhibitions, teaching, and committees, photographs, art work, personal papers, and printed material. Additional McCausland material donated later from the estate of Berenice Abbott include biographical materials, project files, writings, and printed materials.
McCausland, Elizabeth
Provenance
Elizabeth McCausland donated the bulk of her papers in several installments from 1956 to 1961. An unknown donor, perhaps her literary executor, donated additional papers sometime after her death in 1965. It appears that McCausland originally donated her research files on Marsden Hartley, measuring 10 linear feet, to the Whitney Museum, who then lent them to the Archives for microfilming in 1966, and donated them sometime thereafter. McCausland originally donated files of newspaper clippings and offprints of her articles to the The New York Public Library, who gave them to the Archives in 1968. Additional McCausland material from the estate of Berenice Abbott was donated to the Archives in 2009.
Separated Material
Material separated from the collection includes some issues of Camera Work (Vol. 30, 47, 49/50), which were combined with other issues in an artificial collection created by the Archives at some earlier point.
Related Material
Related material found in the Archives includes a sound recording from a symposium on Marsden Hartley, of which McCausland was a participant, held at the Portland Museum of Art in 1961. The Frank Kleinholz papers contain a recorded interview of McCausland done in 1944-1945 for radio station WNYC. Some of McCausland's correspondence is found in the G. Alan Chidsey papers; Chidsey served as a trustee of the Marsden Hartley estate.
Alternative Forms Available
The bulk of this collection was digitized in 2008 and 2015 and is available on the Archives of American Art's website.
Materials generally not scanned include some newsclippings and publications that were either too fragile or not relevant, although some publications that appeared to be of interest to her were scanned. Other items that typically were not scanned include McCausland's student records, auction catalogs, proofs and multiple drafts of published articles, copy prints and negatives of photographs made by the Archives, photographs of works of art (except for those in the catalogue raisonne files of the Marsden Hartley series), duplicate material, and any published material that is widely available elsewhere. In some cases, only the cover and title pages for publications were scanned.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Biographical Note
Elizabeth McCausland, the art critic and writer, was born in Wichita, Kansas in 1899. She attended Smith College, receiving her Bachelor's degree in 1920 and her Master's in 1922. Beginning in 1923, she worked as a general reporter for The Springfield Republican (Springfield, Massachusetts). After several years, she began to review art exhibitions and soon became an established art critic. In the course of her work, she began to develop friendships with artists, such as Alfred Stieglitz and Arthur Dove. During these early years, she also wrote poetry and designed and printed limited edition publications on her private press.
McCausland moved to New York in 1935, but continued to contribute a weekly art column to The Springfield Republican until it suspended publication in 1946. From the mid-1930s on, she worked primarily as a freelance writer and art critic, contributing articles to publications such as Parnassas, The New Republic, and Magazine of Art. In the latter part of her career, her writings focused more on art history and special studies on artists.
In the late-1930s, McCausland collaborated with the photographer Berenice Abbott on the Federal Art Project book, Changing New York, for which she provided the text to Abbott's now-famous photographs of New York City neighborhoods, architecture, and street scenes. She studied and wrote about photography, including numerous articles on the photographer Lewis Hine (of whose work she organized a retrospective exhibition at the Riverside Museum in 1939), and was appointed to the Advisory Committee of the Museum of Modern Art's Department of Photography in 1944.
McCausland went on to organize other exhibitions, including a show of contemporary work, "The World of Today" (Berkshire Museum, 1939), shows of silk screen prints (Springfield Museum of Fine Arts, March 1940 and New York State Museum, Summer 1940), and a photography show, "Photography Today" (A.C.A. Gallery, 1944). In the late 1930s, she embarked upon a study of "the status of the artist in America from colonial times to the present, with especial attention to the relation between art and patronage," which continued over twenty years (and was never completed) and for which she received a Guggenheim fellowship in 1943.
In addition to her other writing, during the 1940s, McCausland carried out studies on the artists, E. L. Henry and George Inness, which resulted in exhibitions at the New York State Museum in 1942 and the George Walter Vincent Smith Art Museum in 1946, respectively and publications (a report on Henry and a book on Inness). From 1948 to 1949, she carried out an extensive study of the painter, Alfred H. Maurer, organizing an exhibition, "A. H. Maurer: 1868-1932," which showed at the Walker Art Center and the Whitney Museum of American Art in 1949, and publishing the biography, A. H. Maurer, in 1951. In 1950, she worked as a special consultant on the American Processional exhibition at the Corcoran Gallery and as editor of the accompanying book. Shortly thereafter, she began a study of Marsden Hartley for a monograph, which was published in 1952, and she helped organize the Hartley exhibition at the University of Minnesota that same year. She continued the Hartley study on larger scale for a planned biography and catalogue raisonne; although she continued to work on it off and on for the next decade, the project was never completed.
McCausland published other books, including Careers in the Arts (1951), and undertook other research and consulting projects, such as photo-editing Carl Sandburg's Poems of the Midwest (1946), conducting surveys of art and advertising for an article in Magazine of Art and of art education for Cooper Union Art School, and contributing yearly articles on art to various encyclopedias. At different times throughout her career, she supplemented her income by taking teaching positions. She taught courses on art history at Sarah Lawrence College from 1942 to 1944 and at Barnard College in 1956, as well as courses at the Design Laboratory (1939) and the New School for Social Research (1946). She also gave numerous lectures and speeches on various art topics, and regularly participated in conferences and symposiums. Towards the end of her career, she was publishing less, but was still involved in many projects, most notably the Hartley study.
McCausland was a tireless promoter of the arts, and often an advocate for artists. Even though her work was well-known among certain art circles, she never received the recognition as a writer that she deserved. Nor was she ever able to free herself from the pressure of writing for a living. Continually suffering from poor health, she died on May 14, 1965.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of art critic, writer, and historian Elizabeth McCausland measure approximately 45 linear feet and date from 1838 to 1995, with the bulk of the material dating from 1920 to 1995. The collection provides a vast accumulation of data on various artists and aspects of American art, especially the early American modernists and the Federal Arts Projects. Papers include McCausland's extensive research and writing files, particularly on Marsden Hartley, E. L. Henry, Lewis Hine, George Inness, and Alfred H. Maurer. McCausland's correspondence with artists includes a substantial amount with Arthur Dove and Alfred Stieglitz. Her collaborative work with Berenice Abbott on the Changing New York book and series of photographs is well-documented within the collection. Also found are general writings, subject files, files relating to exhibitions, teaching, and committees, photographs, art work, personal papers, and printed material. Additional McCausland material from the estate of Berenice Abbott include biographical materials, project files, writings, and printed materials.
McCausland's personal papers consist of appointment books and engagement calendars, scrapbooks, student papers, works printed on her private press, financial records, biographical material, and scattered memorabilia, which together document other aspects of her life apart from her work. Correspondence includes incoming and outgoing letters along with enclosures, dating from McCausland's time as a journalist for The Springfield Republican in the 1920s and 1930s to her time as a freelance writer, art critic, and historian (1940s-1960s) and mostly concerning professional matters. Also included is a substantial amount of correspondence with artists, particularly Arthur Dove and Alfred Stieglitz, and some personal correspondence with her mother. General writings consists primarily of copies of McCausland's speeches and lectures on various art topics in addition to her early poems (dating from the 1930s) and scattered essays and articles.
The most extensive part of the collection is comprised of McCausland's research and writing files pertaining to large research and curatorial projects, such as ones on the artists Alfred H. Maurer and Marsden Hartley (which was begun by the American Art Research Council and subsequently taken over by McCausland), and one for the American Processional exhibition at the Corcoran Gallery in 1950. A wide variety of smaller projects are also well-documented in the series Other Research and Writing Files, including ones on E. L. Henry, Lewis Hine, George Inness, her collaborative work with Berenice Abbott on the Changing New York book and series of photographs. Numerous other artists and art topics are covered as well, such as Arthur Dove, Robert Henri, Jacob Lawrence, Charles Hawthorne, film, and photography. Files for her book Careers in Art (1950), her many speaking and lecture engagements, and editing work are also found in this series. Files consist primarily of correspondence, notes, research material, manuscripts, bibliographies, photographs of works of art, completed research forms for works of art, card index files, and printed material.
Also found are subject files containing printed material, scattered notes and correspondence, and photographs, which may have been used for reference and/or collected in the course of McCausland's research activities; files relating to various exhibitions organized by McCausland from 1939 to 1944, including ones of silk screen prints and modern photography; files relating to courses on art history taught by McCausland, especially the one she taught at Barnard College in 1956; and files stemming from her participation in various art organizations and committees, especially during the time period just before and during the Second World War.
Printed material consists primarily of clippings and tear sheets of McCausland's newspaper articles and columns, which document her contributions to The Springfield Republican from 1923 to 1946, in addition to scattered exhibition catalogs, announcements, books, and miscellaneous publications. Photographs include ones of various artists and works of art, ones from the Farm Security Administration, and ones by photographers, such as Berenice Abbott (including ones from the Federal Art Project book, Changing New York), Barbara Morgan, Weegee, and Edward Weston, among others. Photographs, sometimes annotated or including notes, are scattered throughout her research files. Also included are photographs of McCausland, dating from her childhood. Art work found in the collection includes drawings, prints, and watercolors that were either given to McCausland by the artist or collected by her in the course of her work as an art critic and historian.
Additional material belonging to Elizabeth McCausland and donated by the estate of Berenice Abbott includes biographical material; business and personal correspondence; professional project files and writings, including drafts and research materials related to the book projects Art in America, Conversations with March, and Frank Kleinholz; and printed materials, including reprints of critical essays and articles by McCausland.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 15 series:
Series 1: Personal Papers, 1838, 1920-1951 (Boxes 1-2, 34; 1.5 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1923-1960 (Boxes 2-5; 2.9 linear feet)
Series 3: General Writings, circa 1930-1954 (Boxes 5-6; 0.9 linear feet)
Series 4: Alfred H. Maurer, 1851-1951, bulk 1948-1950 (Boxes 6-9; 3.7 linear feet)
Series 5: American Processional, 1949-1951 (Boxes 10-11; 1.8 linear feet)
Series 6: Marsden Hartley, 1900-1964, bulk 1944-1964 (Boxes 11-21, OV 37; 10 linear feet)
Series 7: Other Research and Writing Files, 1896, 1926-1958 (Boxes 21-25, 31; 4.6 linear feet)
Series 8: Subject Files, 1927-1954 (Boxes 25-26; 1.0 linear feet)
Series 9: Other Exhibition Files, 1939-1941, 1944 (Box 26; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 10: Teaching Files, 1939-1965 (Box 27; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 11: Committee Files, 1936-1960 (Box 27; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 12: Printed Material, 1923-1953 (Boxes 28-32, 34, OV 38, BV 44-47; 4.6 linear feet)
Series 13: Photographs, circa 1905-1950 (Boxes 32-36, OV 37; 1.4 linear feet)
Series 14: Art Work, 1887-1942 (Boxes 33-34, OV 39-43; 0.7 linear feet)
Series 15: Elizabeth McCausland Material from the Estate of Berenice Abbott, 1920-1995 (Boxes 48-53; 5.4 linear feet)
Abbott, Berenice, 1898, Changing New York; American Art Research Council.; Barnard College. -- Faculty; Dove, Arthur Garfield, 1880-1946; Federal Art Project (U.S.); Hartley, Marsden, 1877-1943; Hawthorne, Charles Webster, 1872-1930; Henri, Robert, 1865-1929; Henry, Edward Lamson, 1841-1919; Hine, Lewis Wickes, 1874-1940; Inness, George, 1825-1894; Kleinholz, Frank, 1901-; Lawrence, Jacob, 1917-2000; Maurer, Alfred Henry, 1868-1932; Morgan, Barbara Brooks, 1900-; Stieglitz, Alfred, 1864-1946; United States. Farm Security Administration.; Weegee, 1899-1968; Weston, Edward, 1886-1958; Art criticism--United States; Art critics--New York (State)--New York; Art historians--New York (State)--New York; Art, American; Art, Modern--20th century--United States; Art--Exhibitions--United States; Art--History--Study and teaching; Art--Societies, etc.--United States; Authors--New York (State)--New York; Documentary photography--United States; Drawings; Federal aid to the arts; Modernism (Art)--United States; New York N.Y.--Pictorial works--Photographs; Photographs; Prints; Scrapbooks; Springfield Republican; Watercolors
- Personal Papers, 1838, 1920-1951; Series 1; 1.5 Linear feet Boxes 1-2, 34
  Scope and Contents note
  Series consists of material relating to the more personal aspects of McCausland's life, including appointment books and engagement calendars, scrapbooks, student papers, works printed on her private press in Springfield, Massachusetts, financial records, biographical material, and scattered memorabilia. Scrapbooks include one kept by McCausland, dating from 1937 to 1940, comprised of correspondence from Waldo Leland Cook, Art Young, Max Weber, and Edward Sternberg, clippings, and other printed material (which was disassembled at some previous point in time and exists now as loose items); and one kept by her mother, Belle Noble McCausland, dating from 1920 to 1943, comprised mostly of clippings and empty envelopes from letters received by McCausland (letters were removed at some previous point in time and can now be found amongst correspondence). Student papers include an honors paper written while an undergraduate at Smith College and a copy of her M.A. thesis published in Smith College Studies in Modern Languages (1922). Amongst the memorabilia is a sign from Lake George that, according to a note on it, was given to McCausland by Alfred Stieglitz, presumably some time during the 1930s.
  Also found is material relating to the scrip McCausland received as payment for work at The Springfield Republican in 1933; a car trip McCausland made with Berenice Abbott in 1935; and a testimonial dinner for McCausland "in recognition of her work in the field of art criticism and of her efforts on behalf of all artists" which was held on May 28, 1945 at the Hotel Breevort in New York.
  Arrangement note
  Personal papers are arranged in alphabetical order according to format.
  Existence and Location of Copies note
  This series is partially scanned; early academic records, tax records, duplicates, and poems written by others have not been scanned.
  - Academic Records, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Appointment Books (See also Engagement Calendars) (Box 1)
    - Appointment Books, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Appointment Books, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Appointment Books, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Appointment Books, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Appointment Books, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Appointment Books, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Appointment Books, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Appointment Books, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Appointment Books, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Appointment Books, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Appointment Books, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Biographical Material, 1942-1950 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Book of Poems by Genevieve Taggard, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Curriculum Vitae Material, circa 1920-1951 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Engagement Calendars (See also Appointment Books) (Box 1)
    - Engagement Calendars, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Engagement Calendars, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Financial Records, 1944-1946, 1950-1952 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Income Taxes, 1943-1946, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Memorabilia (Box 2)
    - Cover of The New York Mirror, 1838 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Oversized item in Box 34
    - Sign Given to McCausland by Alfred Stieglitz, 1930s (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous (includes childhood photographs), 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Private Press, 1928-1935 (Box 2, Folder 6-8)
  - Private Press, Duplicates, 1928-1935 (Box 2, Folder 9-11)
  - Recommendations, 1935-1936, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Scrapbook Kept by Belle Noble McCausland, 1920-1943 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Scrapbook, 1937-1940 (Box 2, Folder 14-18)
  - The Springfield Republican, Scrip, circa 1933 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Student Papers (Box 2)
    - Special Honors in English (B.A.), [1920] (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - American-Scandinavian Foundation Fellowship, 1922 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - M. A. Thesis, 1922 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Testimonial Dinner for Elizabeth McCausland, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Trip Made by Elizabeth McCausland and Berenice Abbott (Box 2)
    - "Log", 1935 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Maps, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Oversize, Memorabilia (Box 34)
    - Cover of The New York Mirror, 1838 (Box 34)
      Scanned with Box 2, Folder 3
    - Sign Given to McCausland by Alfred Stieglitz, 1930s (Box 34)
      Scanned with Box 2, Folder 4
- Correspondence, 1923-1960; Series 2; 2.9 Linear feet Boxes 2-5
  Series consists primarily of McCausland's professional and, to a lesser extent, personal correspondence, which includes general, artist, and some family correspondence. Correspondence typically consists of letters to and copies of letters from McCausland, along with enclosures (such as clippings and other printed material; contracts, agreements, and other business and financial papers; and proposals and manuscripts) and related material (such as notes, illustrations, and writings). Correspondents include artists, art organizations, museums, curators, editors, publishers, scholars, research institutions, her agent (Mary Squire Abbot), friends, and her mother, Belle Noble McCausland. Correspondence largely documents McCausland's various professional activities as an art critic, art historian, and freelance writer, and her relationships with various figures of the art and publishing worlds before, during, and immediately after the Second World War.
  General correspondence relates to articles and reviews that McCausland wrote for the Springfield Republican; to freelance articles she wrote over the years for various publications, including ones for Parnassus, The New Republic, and Magazine of Art, as well as yearly articles for various encyclopedias (such as Encyclopedia Britannica, Encyclopedia Americana, and Collier Encyclopedia); and to various book projects, including Changing New York (1939), Careers in the Arts (1950), and ones on the artists E. L. Henry, George Inness, and Alfred H. Maurer. General correspondence also relates to her teaching job at Sarah Lawrence College and other courses taught; to various editing projects, including photo-editing Carl Sandburg's Poems of the Midwest and the planned book Art and Advertising; her work as a research consultant on the American Processional exhibition and book, and on other exhibitions; and her involvement in various art and social organization, as well as her participation in various conferences. General correspondence largely documents McCausland's tireless efforts to drum up work, and to fund (through various grants and fellowships) and carry out her many research and writing projects.
  Correspondence from particular artists, including Arthur Dove, Louis Eilshemius, Marsden Hartley, Georgia O'Keeffe, and Alfred Stieglitz, was maintained by McCausland in files separate from general correspondence. Artist correspondence documents her relationships with these artists - particularly well-documented are her relationships with Dove and Stieglitz - and the artists' reactions to her reviews of their shows. Files of artist correspondence also include some of McCausland's own notes on her feelings about or relationship with particular artists.
  Family correspondence consists almost entirely of letters and copies of letters from McCausland to her mother, Belle Noble McCausland. These seem to have originated from the scrapbook kept by McCausland's mother which can be found amongst personal papers.
  See index for List of Notable Correspondents from Series 2